A Guide to the Robert Taylor Preston Papers, 1849-1871 (Bulk 1861-1862)
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Robert Taylor Preston Papers, 1849-1871 (Bulk, 1861-1862)
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1992-003
0.2 cu. ft. 1 box; 1 oversize folder
The collection consists of 218 letters, military orders, notes, certificates of military appointments, and other items, collected or created by Preston between 1849 and 1871, with the majority from the period between May 1861 and December 1862.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Robert Taylor Preston Papers were donated to Special Collections in July 1994.
Alternate Form Available
Transcripts of some materials are available.
Several items from the collection have been scanned. See the "Contents List" for links to images (gifs).
Biographical Information
Robert Taylor Preston was born at Smithfield Plantation in Blacksburg, Virginia, in 1809 to James Patton and Nancy Ann Taylor Preston. He was a student at Hampden-Sydney College from 1825 to 1828. He qualified as a captain of the 75th Regiment of the (Virginia?) Militia in 1830 and was commissioned as Justice of the Peace of Montgomery County in 1837. In 1833, he married Mary Hart (1802-1882) and they had three children: Virginia Ann Emily (1834-1898), Benjamin Hart (1836-1851), and James Patton (1838-1901). Robert Taylor Preston built his residence "Solitude" in the early 1830s, and bequeathed the building to the Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College, now Virginia Tech, after his death. At the start of the Civil War he was appointed a colonel of the volunteers in the Provisional Army of Virginia. In July 1861, he was appointed a colonel of the 28th Virginia Infantry, Confederate States of America, where he served until the infantry's reorganization in April 1862. Beginning in August 1864 he served as a lieutenant colonel and then a colonel of the 4th Virginia Reserves, and surrendered with the troops of General J. E. Johnston in North Carolina in April 1865. After the war he continued to reside at Solitude until his death in 1880.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of 218 letters, military orders, notes, certificates of military appointments, and other items, collected or created by Preston between 1849 and 1871, with the majority from the period between May 1861 and December 1862. The materials include several military orders signed by such members of the Confederate Army as Jubal Early, John B. Floyd, and George E. Pickett, as well as orders written by Preston himself. Also included is a manuscript draft of a broadside written by Preston from Solitude on May 13, 1863, as a call to arms to the men of Roanoke and Montgomery County to repel the Union Army which was in the immediate vicinity; and a pardon signed by President Andrew Jackson on September 10, 1865, granting Preston amnesty for his offenses committed in the recent rebellion.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged chronologically.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Materials
Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities, Montgomery County Branch Papers, Ms62-001. Finding aid available online.
John Preston Deed, Ms2005-014.
John Preston Papers, Ms94-034. Finding aid available online.
Preston Family (Alice Preston Moore Collection) Papers, Ms62-004.
Preston Family (Charles Peale Didier Collection) Papers, Ms1985-020. Finding aid available online.
Smithfield Preston Foundation Papers, Ms1997-002. Finding aid available on the Virginia Heritage database.
William Preston Land Grant, Ms94-027.
Willard Preston Genealogy, Ms2009-121. Finding aid available on the Virginia Heritage database.
George Green Shackelford Papers, Ms1983-008. Finding aid available online.
Index Terms
Persons:
Preston, Robert Taylor, 1809-1880
Families:
Preston family, Solitude, Blacksburg, Va.
Subjects:
Blacksburg (Va.); Civil War; Local/Regional History and Appalachian South; Montgomery County (Va.); United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865
Contents List
- 1829-1849 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Appointment of Preston to rank of Captain in the 5th Militia of the Commonwealth, signed by William B. Giles, Governor, November 3, 1829
  - Appointment of Preston to rank of Lieutenant Colonel in Virginia Militia, signed by David Campbell, Governor, May 26 1837
  - Appointment to rank of Colonel in the Virginia Militia, signed by John M. Patton, Lieutenant Governor, May 25, 1840
    Scope and Contents note
    Page 1 (gif)
  - Invitation to Miss Virginia T. Preston to the Grand Inauguration Ball of Zachary Taylor (U.S. President) and Millard Filmore (Vice-President), March 5, 1849
- May 1861 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Certificate by Governor John Letches regarding the commission to Colonel for Robert Preston, May 5, 1861
  - Special Requisition for ten Kettle Drums and two fifes for use in the 28th Regiment of the Virginia Volunteers to Major Gorgas, Chief of Ordinance, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Va. Forces, Special Order No. 45, Order assigning Robert Preston to duty at Lynchburg. By order of Major General Lee, May 11, 1861
  - From: Lynchburg, Statement of assumption of command of the Virginia Volunteers mustered into service in Lynchburg. Col. R.C.W. Radford will take charge of the companies of cavalry and Col. Robert T. Preston will take charge of the companies of infantry. Signed: JA Early, Colonel Commanding, May 17, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Va. Forces, Orders for organization of local companies under Preston. Signed: JA Early, May 18, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Va. Forces, Order placing Lieutenant Col. R. S. Brinks under the command of Robert Preston. Signed: JA Early, May 18, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Va. Forces, Order No. 4, List of eight rules to be observed in camps and quarters of the Va. Volunteers. Signed: JA Early, Colonel Commanding, May 18, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Camp Lee, Order appointing Sergeant Thomas Lewis to Sergeant Major. By order of Robert Preston, May 19, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Camp Lee, Order, Private Gillian M. Burwell is assigned to the position of secretary. By order of Robert Preston, May 19, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Camp Lee, Order, Lt. Edmund Goods is appointed to captain of the Regiment. By order of Robert T. Preston, May 19, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Virginia Volunteers, Lynchburg. Orders, Collection of the votes of all persons in the military service of the State regarding the ratification or rejection of the Ordinance of Secession as well as the amendment to the Constitution of Virginia upon the subject of Taxation. Signed: JA Early, Colonel Commanding, May 20, 1861
  - From: Camp Lee, Virginia Volunteers, Orders, All company officers of the regiment will take rank in several grades according to the date when each company was mustered. Levels A - K, May 20, 1861
  - From: Camp Lee, Reminder to those applying to at the Head Quarters of the commandant, Regiment is reminded office hours are strictly limited to times noted on order of the day. Signed: R. C. Allen, May 23, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Va. Volunteers, Order No. 8, Instructions that Capt. Jordan's and Hughes' companies are no longer attached to Col. Robert Preston's regiment and must move to Richmond by railroad. Capt. Kent's and Capt. Williams' companies will move in place of the two listed above. Also included are instructions for Robert Preston to move troops to Manassas Junction. Miles Baxton of Capt. Williams company is to be discharged from service and stricken from rolls. By order of JA Early, Col. Commanding, May 25, 1861
  - Order No. 10, Instructions for the camp to be ready to march out at 4 o'clock tomorrow morning. By order of Col. Robert T. Preston, May 26, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Department of Alexandria, Camp Pickens. General Order: List of eighteen general orders to be followed. Signed: Thomas Jordan, May 28, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Department of Alexandria, Camp Pickens. Special Order: List of men temporarily detailed on extra duty in the Quarter Masters. Department. Includes Col. Preston and some of his regiment. By order of General Bonham, Signed: Thomas Jordan, May 28, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Department of Alexandria, Camp Pickens. General Orders: List of eighteen regulations observed in this camp without variation until otherwise directed. By order of Brig. General Bonham, Signed: Thomas Jordan, May 28, 1861
  - From: Camp Pickens. Order No 11: Instructions regarding men firing guns and pistols within the encampment. By order of Robert T. Preston, May 28, 1861
  - From: Department of Alexandria, Camp Pickens. Instructions for men. Signed: Sam. W. Melton, May 28, 1861
  - From: Department of Alexandria, Camp Pickens. Instructions for Col. Preston to detail some of his men to 8 o'clock guard duty. By order of Brig. General Bonham, Signed: Sam. W. Melton, May 28, 1861
  - From: Department of Alexandria, Camp Pickens. General Order: Detailed instructions and expectations of companies during the 8 o'clock AM guard duty patrol. By order of Thomas Jordan, May 28, 1861
  - From: Department of Alexandria, Camp Pickens. Letter to Robert T. Preston regarding his commission. Signed: Sam. W. Melton, May 28, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Department of Alexandria, Camp Pickens. Order instructing Col. Preston to detail his men for general guard duty. By order of Brig. General Bonham, Signed: Thomas Jordan, May 29, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Department of Alexandria. Request that Preston amend the Regiment Report. Signed: W. C. Morgan, May 30, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Department of Alexandria, Camp Pickens. Announcement that Major Bount is Provost Marshall. By order of Brig. General Bonham, Signed: Thomas Jordan, May 30, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Department of Alexandria, Camp Pickens. Order instructing Col. Preston to detail his men for general guard duty. By order of Brig. General Bonham, Signed: Thomas Jordan, May 30, 1861
  - From: Department of Alexandria, Camp Pickens. Order No. 12: Announcement of inspection. By order of Col. Robert T. Preston, May 31, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Department of Alexandria, Camp Pickens. Col. Preston will detail one intelligent private to act as orderly until further orders. By order of Thomas Jordan, May 31, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Department of Alexandria, Camp Pickens. Special Order: An accurate Report must be made as to the exact strength of each regiment. By order of Brig. General Bonham, Signed: Thomas Jordan, May 31, 1861
- June 1-7, 1861 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - From: Head Quarters, Department of Alexandria, Camp Pickens. General Order: Announcement that Hon. William Smith of Virginia, of this department has become a volunteer. By order of General Bonham, Signed: Thomas Jordan, June 1, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Department of Alexandria, Camp Pickens. General Order: Their will be firing exercises with the artillery tomorrow. By order of General Bonham, Signed: Thomas Jordan, June 1, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Department of Alexandria, Camp Pickens. Order instructing Col. Preston to detail his men for general guard duty. By order of Brig. General Bonham, Signed: Thomas Jordan, June 1, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Department of Alexandria, Camp Pickens. Col. Preston will detail at once and daily thereafter a work party to report to Major Thomas H. Williams on for work in the trenches. By order of General Bonham, Signed: Thomas Jordan, June 1, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Department of Alexandria, Camp Pickens. General Order No. 1: Instructions that all members of the command will help entrench camp for defense against all assaults. By order of General Bonham, Signed: Thomas Jordan, June 1, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Department of Alexandria, Camp Pickens. General Order: In accordance with Special Order No. 149 of the Head Quarters of Virginia Forces, Richmond assigning me to the command of the Alexandria line. I have relieved Brig. General. M. L. Bonham of said command. Signed: G. T. Beauregard, Brig. General. Commanding, June 2, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Department of Alexandria, Camp Pickens. Order No. 35: Col. Preston will detail from his command a party to serve as General Guard for the day. By order of Brig. General Beauregard, Signed: Thomas Jordan, June 2, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Department of Alexandria, Camp Pickens. Order No. 34: Orders for Col. Preston's men to escort a supply train to Fairfax station. Signed: Thomas Jordan. 1861, June 2: From: Head Quarters, Department of Alexandria, Camp Pickens. Order No. 33: Inquiry into cartridge and bayonet scabbard requisitions. Signed: Thomas Jordan, June 2, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Department of Alexandria, Camp Pickens. Order No. 36: Notification of command switch to General Beauregard from General Bonham. Signed: Brig. General. M. Bonham, June 2, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Department of Alexandria, Camp Pickens. General Order No. 5: Major Thomas Rhett assigned to duty as Acting Inspector General. By order of Genl. Beauregard, Signed: Fergason, June 3, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Department of Alexandria, Camp Pickens. General Order No. 3: Annulling of the Provost Marshall position. By order of Brig. General Beauregard, Signed: Thomas Jordan, June 3, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, 5th Brigade, Centreville. Letter of request of a regiment inspection report. Signed: Col. Phillip Geobocke, June 3, 1861
  - From: Camp Pickens, Quarter Masters Office. Order No. 37: Col. Preston will furnish a detail of six men for two days to aid the Quarter Masters Dept. in necessary labor. By order of Brig. General Beauregard, Signed: Thomas Jordan, June 3, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Department of Alexandria, Camp Pickens. General Order No. 7: Orders of changes in the command of various companies. By order of Brig. General Beauregard, Signed: Thomas Jordan, June 4, 1861
  - From: Camp Pickens. Order No. 42: Orders to detail for Guard duty. By order of Brig. General Beauregard, Signed: Thomas Jordan, June 5, 1861
  - From: Quarter Masters Office. Request for two carpenters equipped with tools to report to the Quarter Masters office. Signed: John Gilme, June 5, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Department of Alexandria, Camp Pickens. Orders 42-45: Orders concerning the Post Master and Postal concerns as well as officer of the day. Signed: Col. Preston, June 6, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Department of Alexandria, Camp Pickens. Two soldiers, private Thomas Wood, and private McCormick are to be discharged for disability. By order of General Beauregard, Signed: Thomas Jordan, June 6, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Camp Pickens. Order No. 4: Order for the transfer of Capt. Shipord to Col. Preston's command. By Order of Col. Terrett, June 7, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Camp Pickens. Order to detail eight men to report to the Quarter Master's Department. By order of Col. Terrett, June 7, 1861
- June 8-15, 1861 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - From: Head Quarters, Camp Pickens. Special Order No. 2: Contains reassignment of two companies, Craig Mountain Boys and Patty Lagne Rifles. By order of Col. Terrett, Signed: Thomas J Rhett, June 8, 1861
  - From: Camp Pickens, Department of Alexandria. Order: Promotion of Lieut. Henry Allen to instructor. By order of Col. R. T. Preston, June 8, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Camp Pickens. General Order No. 1: Redirection of the Regimental Manning Reports. By order of Col. Terrett, Signed: Thomas J. Rhett, June 8, 1861
  - From: Camp Pickens, Department of Alexandria. Order: Order assigning Craig Mountain Boys to Company K. By order of Col. R. T. Preston, June 8, 1861
  - From: Camp Pickens, Department of Alexandria. Request issued by Col. Preston for cartridge caps. To Col. S. Jones, Chief of Ordinance. Signed: Col. R. T. Preston, June 9, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Camp Pickens. Order to send men to assist Col. Moore. By order of Sam. Britchell, June 10, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Camp Pickens. Order for General Guard duty. By order of Col. Terrett, Signed: Sam. Britchell, June 10, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Camp Pickens. General Order No. 4: Issuance of additional drills for commissioned and non commissioned officers. By order of Col. Terrett, Signed: Thomas J. Rhett, June 10, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Camp Pickens. Order for men to be detailed for General Guard duty. By order of Col. Terrett, Signed: Sam. Britchell, June 11, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Department of Alexandria, Camp Pickens. Request for the dates of commission of two men in Col. Preston's Company. Signed: Thomas Jordan, June 11, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Camp Pickens. Special Order No. 3: Order for all regiments to be ready at a moments notice. Signed: Thomas Jordan, June 11, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Camp Pickens. Special Order No. 4: An orderly sergeant from each regiment will report for guard duty. By order of Col. Terrett, Signed: Thomas J. Rhett, June 11, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Department of Alexandria, Manassas Junction. General Order No. 10: Orders regarding the Army regulations concerning ambulances and shipping wagons. By order of Brig. General Beauregard, Signed: Thomas Jordan, June 12, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Department of Alexandria, Camp at Manassas Junction. General Order No. 12: Orders regarding the large number of applications for leave of Absence. Commanders are expected to approve no applications hereafter. By order of General Beauregard, Signed: Thomas Jordan, June 12, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Camp Pickens. Special Order: All fatigue duty on the trenches are hereby stopped. By order of Col. Terrett, Signed: Thomas J. Rhett, June 12, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Camp Pickens. To: Col. Preston, Detail troops from your regiment to Whittington Railroad Depot. By order of Col. Terrett, Signed: Thomas J. Rhett, June 12, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Camp Pickens, General Order No. 5: Acting Inspector General will commence his inspection tomorrow at 8 o'clock AM. By order of Col. Terrett, Signed: Thomas J. Rhett, June 12, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Department of Alexandria, Manassas Junction. General Order No. 14: Authorization of weapons target practice between 11 and 12 noon daily, under supervision of an officer, By order of General Beauregard, Signed: Thomas Jordan, June 13, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Camp Pickens. To: Col. Preston. Detail from your men a group to report at Eight and one half AM for General Guard duty. By order of Col. Terrett, Signed: by Davis Mitchell, June 13, 1861
  - From: Department of Alexandria, Camp Pickens. Regimental Order: No officer in command of a company will grant leave to more than five privates to be absent at one time. By order of Col. Preston, June 13, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Camp Pickens. Detail W. C. Porter of the Guard. By order of Col. Terrett, Signed: Davis Mitchell, June 14, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Camp Pickens. Col. Preston will Detail one Captain, two Corporals, and twenty men to report to Capt. Mitchell tomorrow at eight and one half AM for General Guard duty. By order of Col. Terrett, Signed: Davis Mitchell, June 14, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Department of Alexandria, Camp Pickens. General Order No. 16: The General is disturbed by the careless discharge of firearms which slaughter men, therefore, No firing will be allowed except between the hours of 11AM and 12PM. It is the duty of commanding officers to observe and punish all. By order of Brig. General Beauregard, Signed: Thomas Jordan, June 14, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Camp Pickens. General Order No. 6: Colonels will see that their regiments be furnished with the colors of the Confederate States. By order of Col. Terrett, Signed: Thomas J. Rhett, June 14, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Camp Pickens. Special Order No.7: The following detail will report at 6 o'clock tomorrow morning to Capt. Harris, One form Col. Strange's and one from Col. Preston's command. By order of Col. Terrett, Signed: Thomas J. Rhett, June 14, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Camp Pickens. To: Col. Preston. Detail 45 men to report at three o'clock PM. By order of Col. Terrett, Signed: Thomas J. Rhett, June 14, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Camp Pickens. To: Col. Preston. Your regiment will not be inspected tomorrow. Signed: Thomas Rhett, June 15, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Camp Pickens. To: Col. Preston. Detail a Blacksmith from Capt. Wingfield's company to report to Major Cabell. By order of Col. Terrett, Signed: Davis Mitchell, June 15, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Camp Pickens. To: Col. Preston. Detail one sergeant two corporals and twenty men to report to Capt. Mitchell at eight and one half AM for General Guard duty. By order of Col. Terrett, Signed: by Davis Mitchell, June 15, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Camp Pickens. To: Col. Preston. Detail three men to report to Doctor Fisher at the Meazles hospital for fatigue duty. By order of Col. Terrett, Signed: Thomas J. Rhett, June 15, 1861
  - rom: Head Quarters, Camp Pickens. Special Order No. 8: The three following named officers will comprise a Board of Survey to meet in Col. Preston's regiment to examine and report on spoiled beef. Capt. Adam Clement, Lieut. W. S. Goggin Jr., Lieut. M. J. Kemper. By order of Col. Terrett, Signed: Thomas J. Rhett, June 15, 1861
  - From: Committee of Survey. Report: The examination of the beef found it to be entirely unfit for use, being very much fly brown. The company did right to refuse it. Signed: A. Clement, Wm. S. Goggin Jr., M. J. Kemper, June 15, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Camp Pickens. The Colonel approves of the proceedings of the Board of Survey (regarding food spoilage) and orders that the beef be thrown away and other issued in it's place. Signed: Thomas Rhett, June 15, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Department of Alexandria, Manassas Junction. Special Order No. 36: By authority from Head Quarters of the Virginia Forces, execute the following transfers involving Wm. D. Robertson, Charles F. Myers, E. Bausbery, and Hugh M. Laughlin. By order of Brig. General Beauregard, Signed: Thomas Jordan, June 15, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Camp Pickens. Special Order No. 9: The Colonels will see that transfers are made. By order of Col. Terrett, Signed: Thomas J. Rhett, June 15, 1861
- June 16-22, 1861 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - From: Head Quarters, Camp Pickens. To: Col. Preston. A party of your men, yesterday, fired their weapons at an embankment. Several of the balls hit the hospital. Use stringent measures in putting a stop to this neglect of orders. Signed: Thomas Rhett, June 16, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Department of Alexandria, Camp at Manassas Junction. General Order No. 17: All officers of the Quarter Master's department, prepare to advance at short notice. All troops will be furnished with ten days rations and forty rounds of ammunition. By order of Brig. General Beauregard, Signed: Thomas Jordan, June 16, 1861
    Page 2 (gif)
  - From: Camp Pickens. Detail for fatigue duty. By order of Col. Terrett, Signed: Thomas J. Rhett, June 16, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Camp Pickens. General Order No. 8: All unattached regiments see that the requirements of General Order No. 17 be completed. By order of Col. Terrett, Signed: Thomas J. Rhett, June 16, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Camp Pickens. General Order No. 7: The Commander directs that General Order No. 12 of Head Quarters, Department of Alexandria be published at evening parade. By order of Col. Terrett, Signed: Thomas J. Rhett, June 16, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Camp Pickens. To: Col. Preston. Detail for tomorrow. By order of Col. Terrett, Signed: Davis Mitchell, June 16, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Camp Pickens. Special Order No. 12: Detail a party to inspect the guard pickets on the Orange and Alexandria Railroad. By order of Col. Terrett, Signed: Thomas J. Rhett, June 18, 1861